Guide to the Records of the Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site and Lamartine Place Historic District 2005-2017 MS 3136
New-York Historical Society
Records of the Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site and Lamartine Place Historic District
2005-2017
New-York Historical Society
Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site and Lamartine Place Historic District (New York, N.Y.)
MS 3136
3 Linear feet in 3 record cartons.
4.87 Gigabytes (1,094 files, 43 folders)
Documentation of the historic preservation efforts to recognize the house at 339 West 29th Street, Manhattan's only extant stop on the Underground Railroad, and home, during the Civil War Draft Riots of July 1863, to the abolitionist Gibbons family, who fled the attacking mob across the adjoining rooftops. In 2009 the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission designated the house and its neighbors the Lamartine Place Historic District, after the mid-19th century development's original name.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Researchers may request view-only remote access to digital materials. A full manifest of the individual files comprising the series is available from the reference librarian on request. Certain digital files may not be accessible due to file corruption or because the library does not have the proprietary software necessary to make the information they contain accessible.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site and Lamartine Place Historic District, via co-chairs Julie M. Finch and Fern Luskin, 2019 (accession no. MS-2019-006).
Arrangement
With some slight alterations (e.g., topical groupings and title expansions), the files in this collection remain in the chronological order in which they were received. Records maintained separately by Fern Luskin are filed after the main sequence.
Historical Note
Beginning in 1846 developers Cyrus Mason and William Torrey built a row of houses on the north side of West 29th Street between Eighth and Ninth Avenues in the Manhattan neighborhood of Chelsea. The predominantly Greek Revival-style buildings faced a green space across the street, Lamartine Park, apparently named for Alphonse de Lamartine, who played a role in the French Revolution of 1848. To boost sales Mason and Torrey rechristened the block "Lamartine Place." (Similarly, West 28th Street became the more distinctive "Fitzroy Place.") The development attracted prominent residents, such as the philanthropists James Sloan Gibbons (1810–1892) and his wife, Abby (Hopper) Gibbons (1801–1893), who purchased No. 19 Lamartine Place in 1852. Noted abolitionists, the Gibbons family made their home a stop on the Underground Railroad, where they usually sheltered, fed, and supplied the needs of several escaping slaves at once. Notable visitors to the home included Horace Greeley, Lydia Maria Child, and William Lloyd Garrison.
The Gibbonses were staunch Republicans who supported the Civil War as an evil necessary to ending slavery. With the discovery that those who could afford a surrogate could buy their way out of conscription, violent mobs (probably organized by agitators) stormed New York on July 13–16, 1863, attacking known sites of abolitionist activity. Aware that their home was likely to be hit, Julia and Lucy Gibbons (daughters of James and Abby) carried some of their belongings over the rooftops to an uncle's house down the street. The mob came on July 14, chanting "Greeley! Gibbons! Greeley! Gibbons!" and looted the home, passing what they could through the windows, trampling what they could not. Forced by the militia to disperse, the rioters regrouped and set fire to 19 Lamartine Place. The house was damaged, but thankfully not destroyed. By then the Gibbons family was ensconced in their relative's home, but still at risk. A friend, finding them there, led them back over the rooftops toward Ninth Avenue and down to a carriage and safety.
Despite the burning of No. 19, Lamartine Place survived the New York City Draft Riots. The street name eventually reverted to West 29th. Its houses stood largely intact into the early 21st century, wearing the minor alterations common to 150-year-old rowhouses. One day in April 2007, Fern Luskin, a professor of art history at LaGuardia Community College and resident of the block, noticed a penthouse addition going up atop one of the houses. Distressed that its increased height would mar the uniform appearance of the row, she began to investigate the legality of the construction. In her research Luskin uncovered the by-then forgotten history of the development, how it had once been called Lamartine Place, and how it had once been home to the abolitionist Gibbons family. Remarkably, their house—now renumbered 339 West 29th Street—was the very one being disfigured by an addition that was erasing its roof and all trace of their Draft Riots escape.
The efforts of Luskin, fellow activist Julie M. Finch, and other concerned residents and elected officials, brought wide recognition to the Hopper Gibbons house as Manhattan's only extant, documented stop on the Underground Railroad. On October 13, 2009, the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission designated 339 West 29th Street and its neighboring buildings the Lamartine Place Historic District. By law, buildings so designated cannot be demolished or altered without consent of the Landmarks Preservation Commission. Despite this, the owner of 339 West 29th Street continued work on the rooftop alteration under expired and revoked permits, claiming (falsely) that construction had happened before the designation. After protracted legal actions, on May 18, 2017, the Landmarks Preservation Commission and the New York City Department of Buildings ruled in favor of the Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site and Lamartine Place Historic District (as Luskin, Finch, and their associates came to be called): they ordered the owner to remove the addition and restore the roofline to its historic height.
For a fuller history of the block and the work of Finch, Luskin, et al., see the Lamartine Place Historic District Designation Report, and Dusica Sue Malesevic, "Preservationists Win: Hopper-Gibbons House Owner Ordered to Subtract Addition" in The Villager, May 24, 2017.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society holds two typescript versions of Lucy Gibbons Morse's "Personal Recollections of the Draft Riots of 1863" in which she describes her family's experiences at 19 Lamartine Place (today's 339 West 29th Street) on July 14, 1863: AHMC - Morse, Lucy Gibbons and F128.44 .M88 Oversize.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents efforts by the Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site and Lamartine Place Historic District, led by Fern Luskin and Julie M. Finch, to recognize and preserve no. 339 West 29th Street (originally called 19 Lamartine Place), Manhattan's only extant stop on the Underground Railroad and home, during the Draft Riots of July 1863, to abolitionists James Sloan and Abby (Hopper) Gibbons, whose family fled across the adjoining rooftops to escape the attacking mob. Through clippings, email printouts, financial records, fliers, letters, press releases, and research notes dating between 2005 and 2017, the collection details the eventual designation by the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission of the Hopper Gibbons House and its neighboring buildings as the Lamartine Place Historic District, and recounts the protracted litigation against an illegal rooftop addition constructed by the owner of 339 West 29th Street.
Abolitionists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Chelsea (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.); Draft Riot, New York, N.Y., 1863; Historic preservation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lamartine Place Historic District (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Underground Railroad -- New York (State) -- New York; Clippings (information artifacts); Compact discs.; Digital file formats.; Financial records.; Fliers (printed matter); Letters (correspondence); Press releases.; Printouts; Research notes.; Testimonies.; Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site and Lamartine Place Historic District (New York, N.Y.) -- Records
- 339 West 29th Street. Department of Buildings violations [5 folders in 1], 2005, 2007, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- 339 West 29th Street. Photos and plans [2 folders in 1], 2007 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Contact lists, to-do lists [3 folders in 1], 2008-? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- [Emails, correspondence, general] [7 folders in 2], 2008 February - December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Four Borough Neighborhood Preservation Alliance, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Historic Districts Council, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission [2 folders in 1], 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- New York Landmarks Conservancy, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- New York State Historic Preservation Office [11 folders in 3], 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10-12)
- Preservation League of New York State [2 folders in 1], 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Gibbons Quaker House, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- [Elected officials and others] [9 folders in 1], 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  Scope and Contents
  Files for Colin Casey / Tom Duane (New York State Senate); Bill Clinton; Gregory Dietrich (Cultural Resource Consulting Group); Justin Ferate (tour guide); Richard N. Gottfried (New York State Assembly); H + H Building Consultants; Jerrold Nadler / Micah Lasher (U.S. House of Representatives, New York's 8th District); Christine Quinn (New York City Council Speaker); Carl Westmoreland / Fergus Bordewich (Underground Railroad scholars).
- Abby Hopper Gibbons @ Swathmore, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Mount Morris Park Community Improvement Association [2 folders in 1], 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Underground Railroad [4 folders in 1], 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
- [Emails, correspondence, general] [9 folders in 2], 2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19-20)
- Fifteenth Street Monthly Meeting & Farmington Quaker Meetinghouse [3 folders in 1], 2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
- New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission [4 folders in 1], 2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
- Press [2 folders in 1], 2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
- 339 West 29th Street. Department of Buildings applications, permits, violations, etc. [6 folders in 1], 2009-2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
- Photos - dated - BSA & court, 2007-2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
- Boilerplate "mission statement," advisory committee, Fern's letter, 2008-2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
- 339 West 29th Street. Department of Buildings violations, FOIA, etc. [5 folders in 1], 2009-2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
- City Council, 2010 January 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- Underground Railroad conference [2 folders in 1], 2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- Gibbons general & backup [2 folders in 1], 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- Loose material, 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- Interview, 2011 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- My [Fern Luskin's?] speech, Victorian Society, 2011 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- Hopper Gibbons timelines [5 folders in 1], 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Lamartine Place Historic District marker unveiling [6 folders in 1], 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- New York City Board of Standards and Appeals [14 folders in 5], 2012 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-13)
- 29th Street Block Association, 2012 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
- Gibbons press clips [5 folders in 2], circa 2008-2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15-16)
- Quaker-formed groups / Women's Prison Association, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
- Friends of Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site fundraiser [6 folders in 1], 2013 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
- New York City Board of Standards and Appeals, 2013 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
- New York State Supreme Court [4 folders in 2], 2013 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20-21)
- Press conferences, 2013 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
- Loose material, [2013?] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
- Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, [2013?] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
- Historic Districts Council financial accounts, 2013-2014 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
- 2nd appeal Gibbons [2 folders in 1], 2014 July (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
- Letters of support, 2014-2015 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
- Loose material, 2014-2015 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
- Historic Districts Council financial accounts, 2015-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
- Advisory committee [2 folders in 1], 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
- Friends of the Hopper Gibbons Underground Railroad Site fundraiser [2 folders in 1], 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- General [4 folders in 1], 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
- Loose material, 2015-2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- New York City Department of Buildings / Community Board 4 [5 folders in 1], 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- New York City Department of Buildings lawsuit [3 folders in 1], 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
- New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission [7 folders in 1], 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
- Press conference, 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- Retainer fiscal agent, 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
- West 29th Street owners, [2016?] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
- New York City Department of Buildings, 2016-2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
- Mailing list [2 folders in 1], 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
- New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission, 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
- Fern Luskin files. Meetings, 2007 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
- Fern Luskin files. 29th Street Certificates of Occupancy & Zoning Code [2 folders in 1], 2007 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
- Fern Luskin files. 339 West 29th Street photos, 2007-2012 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
- Fern Luskin files. 339 West 29th Street Department of Buildings violations, audits [2 folders in 1], 2007-2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
- Fern Luskin files. Correspondence, 2007-2009 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
- Fern Luskin files. Architectural Plans & My Calculations, [2007-2010] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
- Fern Luskin files. Legal Papers, Part 1, 2007-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
- Fern Luskin files. Legal papers, part 2, 2007-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
- Fern Luskin files. Legal papers, part 3, 2007-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
- Fern Luskin files. Petitions, flyers, news clippings [2 folders in 1], 2007-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
- Fern Luskin files. New York State Historic Preservation Office application, 2008 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
- Fern Luskin files. [Award speeches] [3 folders in 1], 2009-2013 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
  Includes Historic Districts Council Grassroots Preservation Award (2009), Victorian Society Preservation Advocacy Award (2011), and Chelsea Reform Democratic Club Doris Corrigan Award (2013).
- Fern Luskin files. Fern's speeches, 2009-2014 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 27)
- Fern Luskin files. CDs of all Hopper-Gibbons House Records & Photographs [5 discs], 2009-2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 28)
  Restricted
  The CDs are restricted, but all files from the discs have been preserved and may be requested separately below (Digital Folder MS3136).
- Fern Luskin files. Digital files from CDs of all Hopper-Gibbons House Records & Photographs, 2009-2017 (Digital-folder MS3136)
  This folder contains 1,094 digital files transferred off the 5 CDs in Box 3, Folder 28. Files primarily include graphic files (JPG, PNG, etc.) and Office files (Word, PDF, PowerPoint, etc.).
  Conditions Governing Access
  Researchers may request view-only remote access to digital materials. A full manifest of the individual files comprising the series is available from the reference librarian on request. Certain digital files may not be accessible due to file corruption or because the library does not have the proprietary software necessary to make the information they contain accessible.